Guide to the R.C. Maxwell Company Records, 1891-2001 and undated RL.01071
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
R.C. Maxwell Company records
1891-2001 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
R.C. Maxwell Co
RL.01071
135 Linear Feet
R.C. Maxwell Company of Trenton, N.J., was one of the earliest enduring outdoor advertising companies, founded in 1894 by Robert Chester Maxwell (1873-1955) and continued to operate primarily in the New Jersey, New York and Pennsylvania area until the company was sold in 2000. The R.C. Maxwell Company Records span the years 1891-2001 and include photographs and negatives, videocassettes, ledgers and account books, scrapbooks, correspondence and legal papers relating to the company's operations in outdoor advertising. Photographs and negatives in several formats (film, glass negatives, polaroid prints) document billboard designs for a variety of advertisers as well as depicting billboard and electric sign structures and their location relative to the surrounding environment. Urban locations include Times Square in New York and the Atlantic City, N.J., Boardwalk, where a number of photographs also document the Miss America beauty pageant parade and other parades in which the R.C. Maxwell Company participated. A few photographs document billboard construction and erection; there are also photographs of the Maxwell family and of Maxwell company staff and employees. Scrapbooks contain images of billboards and wall paintings produced by the Maxwell company as well as by David L. Clark, a High Point, N.C. artist and sign painter who was R.C. Maxwell's guardian. Other scrapbooks document primarily Coca-Cola signs of the early 20th century, as well as World War I support efforts including the U.S. Food Administration (under the direction of Herbert Hoover), the U.S. Fuel Administration, and Liberty Bond campaigns. Companies represented in the collection include the Boardwalk Advertising Signs Co., C&B Electric Signs Co., Trenton Advertising Co., and Trenton Poster Advertising Co. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
118,350 Items
Online Items
Selected items from this collection have been digitized and are available in: Resource of Outdoor Advertising Descriptions (ROAD) - Duke Digital Collections
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
Some fragile documents are closed to use. Preservation photocopies are available in the collection.
Negatives are restricted for preservation reasons. Patrons should view prints. Requests to view negatives under special circumstances may be submitted to the Head of Research Services and will be considered on a case-by-case basis. Nitrate negatives are closed to researchers.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The R.C. Maxwell Company Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts in 1996-2005.
Historical Note
1873 R. (Robert) C. (Chester) Maxwell born
1870s? David L. Clark, an artist who worked in the southeastern US and lived in High Point, N.C., adopted R.C. Maxwell.
1880s? Ran away from the home of David L. Clark; eventually became a sign painter.
1894 Founded an outdoor advertising firm, the R.C. Maxwell Company of Trenton, N.J., at age 21.
1917-1918 During World War I, he served as chief of the Outdoor Advertising Section of the Public Information Division, U.S. Food Administration
1919 The company began creating electric advertising signs.
1923 R.C. Maxwell Company merged with the Trenton Poster Advertising Company and moved to the building at 725 E. State Street in Trenton, N.J.
1920s R.C. Maxwell Company established the Electric Sign Manufacturing Plant in Atlantic City, N.J. to create electric spectacular signs.
1954 R.C. Maxwell died.
2000 R.C. Maxwell Company sold to Interstate Outdoor.
R.C. Maxwell Company of Trenton, N.J., was one of the earliest enduring outdoor advertising companies. Founded in 1894 by Robert Chester Maxwell (1873-1954), the business followed burgeoning industry trends, beginning with a variety of outdoor advertising signage along New Jersey and New York roadways as well as at tourist destinations like Atlantic City, N.J., and New York's Times Square. With the commercial development of the incandescent bulb after World War I, the company began creating electric advertising signs in 1919. Maxwell saw great potential in these spectacular signs and established the Electric Sign Manufacturing Plant in Atlantic City, N.J. in the 1920s. This subsidiary created such giant ads as a 50-foot Colgate thermometer that was placed atop a building on the Atlantic City Boardwalk in 1922. The billboards and spectaculars themselves served as a form of advertising for the company, which displayed slogans such as Maxwell Did It and Maxwell Hits alongside its client's signs. R.C. Maxwell owned numerous billboards in Atlantic City, N.J., and a large number of pictures in this collection are located on the Atlantic City boardwalk.
Collection Overview
The R.C. Maxwell Company Records span the years 1891-2001 and include photographs and negatives, videocassettes, ledgers and account books, scrapbooks, correspondence and legal papers relating to the company's operations in outdoor advertising. Photographs and negatives in several formats (film, glass negatives, polaroid prints) document billboard designs for a variety of advertisers as well as depicting billboard and electric sign structures and their location relative to the surrounding environment. Urban locations include Times Square in New York and the Atlantic City, N.J., Boardwalk, where a number of photographs also document the Miss America beauty pageant parade and other parades in which the R.C. Maxwell Company participated. A few photographs document billboard construction and erection; there are also photographs of the Maxwell family and of Maxwell company staff and employees. Scrapbooks contain images of billboards and wall paintings produced by the Maxwell company as well as by David L. Clark, a High Point, N.C. artist and sign painter who was R.C. Maxwell's guardian. Other scrapbooks document primarily Coca-Cola signs of the early 20th century, as well as World War I support efforts including the U.S. Food Administration (under the direction of Herbert Hoover), the U.S. Fuel Administration, and Liberty Bond campaigns. Companies represented in the collection include the Boardwalk Advertising Signs Co., C&B Electric Signs Co., Trenton Advertising Co., and Trenton Poster Advertising Co.
Approximately 15,000 photographs, dating up to around 1952, have been described in the searchable ROAD Database (Resource of Outdoor Advertising Descriptions). The numbered and indexed black-and-white photographs and negatives (along with a limited number of glass negatives) include images of billboard and electric spectacular executions (illuminated billboards); road shots showing the approach views to billboard structures; images of Maxwell advertising structures; and images of urban and rural billboard displays in various states, primarily Pennsylvania and New Jersey, including a number of images of Times Square in New York and the Atlantic City, N.J. boardwalk. Because the majority of photographs show the billboards in their surroundings, the images provide a snapshot of the people and buildings near the billboard.
Collection Arrangement
Arranged into five series: Administrative Files, Ledgers and Account Books, Scrapbooks, Photographs and Negatives.
Related Material
Related Materials may be found in the following collections of the Hartman Center:
Burr Robbins Papers
Duplex Advertising Company. Billboard Images and Records
Garrett Orr Papers
Howard Scott Papers
John E. Brennan Outdoor Advertising Survey Reports
John F. Hogan Papers
John Paver Papers
Naegele Outdoor Records
Ohio Outdoor Advertising Corporation Records
Outdoor Advertising Association of America (OAAA) Archives
Outdoor Advertising Association of America Poster Designs
Outdoor Advertising Association of America Slide Library
Porter Advertising Billboard Sketches
Robert A. Hamer Papers
Strobridge Lithographing Company Advertisements
Glass plate negatives; Billboards -- 1970-1980; Billboards -- 1960-1970; Billboards -- Pictorial works; Billboards -- New York (State) -- New York -- History -- Pictorial works; Billboards -- 1900-1940; Billboards; Billboards -- 1950-1960; Billboards -- 1940-1950; Videocassettes; New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs; Scrapbooks; Boardwalks -- New Jersey -- Atlantic City -- 1920-1930; New York (State) -- Commerce; Photographs; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States -- History; Advertising executives -- United States; Advertising executives; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Boardwalks -- New Jersey -- Atlantic City -- 1930-1940; Advertising, Outdoor -- New York -- Pictorial works; Advertising, Outdoor -- New Jersey -- Pictorial works; Advertising, Outdoor -- Pictorial works; Advertising; Advertising, Outdoor -- Pennsylvania -- Pictorial works; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States -- Pictorial works; Atlantic City (N.J.) -- Pictorial works; Advertising agencies -- History; Advertising agencies; Advertising -- United States -- History; Advertising -- History; Times Square (New York, N.Y.); Miss America Pageant; World War, 1914-1918; Times Square (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Boardwalks -- New Jersey -- Atlantic City -- 1950-1960; Boardwalks -- New Jersey -- Atlantic City -- 1940-1950; Electric signs -- History; Electric signs; High Point (N.C.); Atlantic City (N.J.); Trenton (N.J.); Negatives (photographs); New York (N.Y.); World War, 1914-1918 -- Food supply -- United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- Finance -- United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- Social aspects -- United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- Posters; Pennsylvania -- Commerce; Pennsylvania -- Photographs; New Jersey -- Commerce; New Jersey -- Pictorial works; New Jersey -- Social life and customs; Coca-Cola Company; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Maxwell, Robert Chester, 1873-1955; R.C. Maxwell Co; United States Food Administration; United States. Fuel Administration
- Administrative Files, 1891-1995 and undated, 24 boxes
  - General Office Files, 1891-1995 and undated
    Scope and Contents note
    Subseries scope/content note.
    - Agreement with Modern Tobacco Barn Company, 1891 (Box 1)
    - Appraisal of 8x10 camera, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Boardwalk Advertising Signs, Inc.
      - Contracts and incorporation, 1928-1929 (Box 1)
      - Financial statements, 1928-1932 (Box 1)
      - Legal and corporate papers, 1927-1932 (Box 1)
      - Memoranda, 1931-1932 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous financial, 1929-1931 and undated (Box 1)
    - C&B Electric Sign Company
      - Notes of incorporation, minutes, etc., 1913-1924 (Box 1)
    - Calendar, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Centennial celebration, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1925 (Box 1)
      - Cable to Chester Maxwell, 1942 (Box 1)
      - Letter from Coca-Cola Archives relating to R.C. Maxwell Company images, 1994 (Box 1)
      - Use of image in Mercer Business, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Herbert Hoover
      - Dinner, 1919 (Box 1)
      - Hoover National Republican Club, 1920 (Box 1)
    - House advertisement layout, Good Neighbors, with 1937 photograph, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Leases, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Maxwell family
      - D.L. Clark materials, 1912-1980 and undated (Box 1)
      - Lawrenceville (Pa.) School calendar, 1914 (Box 1)
    - Minutes
      - Minutes, notes of incorporation, 1904-1917 (Box 1)
      - Minutes of Board meetings, 1917-1924 (Box 1)
      - Minutes of Board meetings, 1965-1985, 1 of 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Minutes of Board meetings, 1965-1985 (continued), 2-3 of 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous designs, undated (Box 2)
    - Photocopies of Atlantic City photographs, 1930s (Box 2)
    - Printed material
      - DuPont, 1916 (Box 2)
      - Hoover as an Executive, by Will Irwin 1920 (Box 2)
      - OAAA Copy Ideas, circa 1965-1967 (Box 2)
      - Postcards, 1913 and undated (Box 2)
        [Includes 1913 season pass to Steeplechase Park, Atlantic City, N.J.]
      - R.C. Maxwell Company brochure, circa 1993 (Box 2)
      - Report of Industrial Conference, 1920 (Box 2)
      - Signs of the Times article on use of helicopters in billboard erection, 1951 (Box 2)
      - Testimonial to Gurden W. Wattles, 1918 (Box 2)
        [Gurgen Wattles was a banker and financier primarily based in Omaha, Neb. He was appointed Federal Food Administrator for Nebraska during World War I, by the U.S. Food Administration.]
      - The Importance of Advertising in War Time, by William Colver, undated (Box 2)
      - Trenton Fact Book, 1980 (Box 2)
      - Trenton-Made Exposition, 1925 (Box 2)
      - U.S. Employment Service Bulletin, 1918 (Box 2)
        [On jobs for returning servicemen.]
    - Proof book of advertisements that appeared in Advertising Age, 1948 (Box 2)
    - Proposal for Wrigley's spectacular in Atlantic City, undated (Box 2)
    - Resolutions, 1965-1989 (Box 2)
    - Speech, The New Efficiency in Public and Private Service, by Julian Barnes, 1920 (Box 2)
    - Stationery and letterhead, 1890s, 1912 and undated (Box 2)
    - Stock redemption agreement, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Trenton Advertising Company
      - Legal and corporate binder, 1930-1943 (Box 2)
    - World War I--War effort
      - Anti-prohibition organizations, 1919 (Box 2)
      - Draft registration, 1918 (Box 2)
      - Final report, Advertising Section, to Ben Allen, 1918 (Box 2)
      - Hoover Overseas and War Service Organizations Directory, 1914-1924, 1929 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1918-1925 (Box 2)
      - Relief organizations, 1919-1920 (Box 3)
      - U.S. Employment Service, 1919 (Box 3)
      - U.S. Food Administration
        - Chronological sketch and directory of members, 1917-1918 (Box 3)
        - Correspondence, 1917-1929, 13 folders (Box 3)
        - Reunion dinner, 1923 (Box 3)
        - Save Food poster design, 1918 (Box 3)
      - U.S. Fuel Administration, 1919 (Box 3)
      - Victory Loan/Liberty Loan programs, 1919 (Box 3)
    - Original correspondence closed to researchers (Box 4 (CLOSED))
      [Use copies are in collection.]
  - Artifacts, undated
    - Camera with case, undated (Box 5)
    - Traffic survey tape, undated (Box 6)
  - Card Files, 1930s-1990s
    - Postings by client, 1930s-1960s (Box 7)
    - Postings by client, 1950s-1990s (Box 8)
    - Trenton area posters by client, 1945-1968 (Box 9)
  - Poster Designs, 1952-1989
    - Advertising, undated (Box 10)
    - Automotive, undated, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Automotive care and repair, 1973-1988 (Box 10)
    - Banking, undated (Box 10)
    - Beverages (alcoholic), 1963-1969 (Box 10)
    - Beverages (non-alcoholic), 1962 (Box 10)
    - Boating, 1987 (Box 10)
    - Clothing, 1961-1973 (Box 10)
    - Credit card, undated (Box 10)
    - Department store, 1971 (Box 10)
    - Electronics/Appliances/Technology, undated (Box 10)
    - Events, 1975-1987 (Box 10)
    - Farming, 1968-1986 (Box 11)
    - Furniture, 1966 (Box 11)
    - Health, undated (Box 11)
    - Holiday shopping, undated (Box 11)
    - Hotels/Inns/Motels, undated (Box 11)
    - Housing/Living (apartments, communities, condos), undated, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Jewelry store, 1986 (Box 11)
    - Laundromat, undated (Box 11)
    - Newspaper, undated (Box 11)
    - Non-profit organizations, 1967-1989 (Box 11)
    - Personal messages, undated (Box 11)
    - Pest control, undated (Box 11)
    - Political, undated (Box 11)
    - Public service announcements, undated (Box 11)
    - Radon, undated (Box 11)
    - Real estate, undated (Box 12)
    - Restaurants, 1952-1987, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Schools, undated (Box 12)
    - Shopping centers, 1987 (Box 12)
    - Sunscreen, undated (Box 12)
    - Tiling, 1987 (Box 12)
    - Transportation, undated (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous poster designs, undated (Box 12)
  - Printing Blocks and Plates, undated
    - Printing Blocks
      - Amoco (Box 13)
      - Bromo Seltzer (Box 13)
      - Buick (Box 13)
      - Camel (Box 13)
      - Chesterfield (Box 13)
      - Clairol (Box 13)
      - Fatima (Box 13)
      - Harwood's (Box 13)
      - Hotel Dennis (Box 13)
      - Noxzema (Box 13)
      - R.C. Maxwell Company (Box 13)
      - R.C. Maxwell Company (Box 14)
      - R.C. Maxwell Company (Box 15)
      - Robbinsville Mobile Homes Sales (Box 15)
      - Seagrams (Box 15)
      - Sherwin-Williams (Box 15)
      - Trenton National Bank (Box 15)
      - Wesson Oil (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous designs (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous designs (continued) (Box 16)
    - Printing Plates
      - Maxwell Service (28 plates) (Box 17)
      - Amoco, Camel (Box 17)
      - Atlantic City scene (Box 17)
      - Broad St. Bank (Box 17)
      - Chesterfield (4 plates) (Box 17)
      - Chevrolet, Camel (Box 17)
      - Coca-Cola (Box 17)
      - Exide Battery (Box 17)
      - General Tire (Box 17)
      - King Midas Flour (Box 17)
      - Princeton Worsted Mills (2 plates) (Box 17)
      - Schenley (Box 17)
      - Spud Cigarettes (Box 17)
  - Public Relations/Publicity Photograph File, 1900s-1980s
    - Calendar images, for 1994 calendar, undated, 14 folders (Box 18)
    - Centennial celebration, 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Competitive structures, 1951 (Box 18)
    - Maxwell family photographs, 1900s-1960s (Box 18)
    - NADA conference, 1947 (Box 18)
    - New Jersey Education Association, undated (Box 18)
    - PR file
      - Numbered photographs A48-2828, 1916-1931 and undated, 67 folders (Box 18)
      - Numbered photographs 2845-12088, 1931-1953, 78 folders (Box 19)
      - Numbered photographs 12317-26431, 1953-1969 (Box 20)
      - Miscellaneous numbered and loose photographs, 1910s-1980s, 10 folders (Box 20)
      - Selected images from glass negatives, 1900s-1910s, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - South Carolina duplicates, 1890s-1910s (Box 20)
      - Unnumbered photographs, 1890s-1994, 14 folders (Box 20)
    - Staff photographs, 1952-1989 and undated, 1-6 of 23 folders (Box 20)
    - Staff photographs, 1952-1989 and undated (continued), 7-23 of 23 folders (Box 21)
    - WWI war effort, U.S. Food Administration, (3 folders) (Box 21)
    - Mounted photographs
      - Atlantic City, 1924 and 1938 (Box 21)
      - D.L. Clark scrapbook, 1890s-1910s, 2 folders (Box 21)
      - General Motors spectacular, 1920s (Box 21)
      - Public service bulletins, circa 1940s (Box 21)
      - R.C. Maxwell Co. office and art studio, undated (Box 21)
      - Seagrams spectacular, New York, circa 1939 (Box 21)
  - Oversize Materials
    [large-format items removed from other series.]
    - Boardwalk Advertising Signs, Co., contracts and financial papers, 1928-1931, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - C&B Electric Sign Company, incorporation and dissolution papers, 1913-1925 (Box 22)
    - Clippings, 1873-1999 (Box 22)
      [Includes R.C. Maxwell obituary notice, article on the murder of Harry Maxwell, and news reports of lawsuit brought by Chester Maxwell.]
    - Maxwell house advertisements, 1930-1994 and undated, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Photocopies of scrapbook pages, circa 1920s (Box 22)
    - Photograph, Coca-Cola sign on bridge (D.L. Clark Co.?), 1910s (Box 22)
    - Photograph, Maxwell family, undated (Box 22)
    - Photograph, R.C. Maxwell staff, undated (Box 22)
    - Printed material, Greater Trenton newsletter, 1918 (Box 22)
    - Printed material, Instructions for the Use of Wallmaster, Wall Washing Machines, Inc., undated (Box 22)
    - R.C. Maxwell Company, Incorporation and other papers, 1910-1960 and undated (Box 22)
    - World War I--War effort, U.S. Food Administration, 1918-1923 (Box 22)
    - World War I--War effort, U.S. Fuel Administration, 1918-1919 (Box 22)
    - Photograph, Pepsodent animation sequence, 1931 (Box 23)
    - World War I--War effort, U.S. Food Administration, poster designs, 1917-1918, 3 folders (Box 23)
      [Some items are extremely fragile.]
  - Audiovisual Materials, 1994
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restriction on Access: Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
    - 100 Years of Outdoor 1894-1994: A Visual History of the R. C. Maxwell Company. 1994. Format: VHS. TRT: 15:00 (Box 24)
- Ledgers and Account Books, 1901-1952, 51 boxes
  - Bethlehem Poster Advertising & Sign Co.
    - Trial balance, 1920-1922 (Box LA1)
  - Boardwalk Advertising Signs, Inc.
    - Stock shares certificates book, undated (Box LA1)
    - Accounts, 1929-1931 (Box LA2)
    - Accounts, 1929-1932 (Box LA2)
    - Receipt book, 1929-1930 (Box LA2)
  - Cedarsafe Co.
    - Order book, 1908-1910 (Box LA3)
  - Trenton Advertising Company
    - Account binder 1--Leases, 1923-1934, 4 folders (Box LA4)
    - Account binder 2 (accounts), 1912 Jan.-1913 Dec. (Box LA4)
    - Account binder 3--Trenton and New Jersey towns, 1924-1932, 5 folders (Box LA5)
    - Account binder 4--Folder 1 of 3, 1920-1923, 3 folders (Box LA6)
    - Account binder 5--Folder 1 of 1 (personal account records), 1923 Apr.-June (Box LA6)
    - Account binder 6--Folder 1 of 6 (check register), 1916 Jan.-Oct. (Box LA7)
    - Account binder 6--Folder 2 of 6 (check register/sales record), 1916 (Box LA7)
    - Account binder 6--Folder 3 of 6 (accounts payable record/personal account records), 1915-1916 (Box LA7)
    - Account binder 6--Folder 4 of 6 (personal account records/sales records), 1915 (Box LA8)
    - Account binder 6--Folder 5 of 6 (sales records/check register), 1915 (Box LA8)
    - Account binder 6--Folder 6 of 6 (check register), 1915 (Box LA8)
    - Account binder 7--Folder 1 of 7 (cash received), 1917 (Box LA9)
    - Account binder 7--Folder 2 of 7 (cash received/sales record), 1917 (Box LA9)
    - Account binder 7--Folder 3 of 7 (sales record), 1917 (Box LA9)
    - Account binder 7--Folder 4 of 7 (accounts payable record), 1917-1918 (Box LA10)
    - Account binder 7--Folder 5 of 7 (cash received), 1918 (Box LA10)
    - Account binder 7--Folder 6 of 7 (cash received/sales record), 1918 (Box LA10)
    - Account binder 7--Folder 7 of 7 (personal account records/sales records), 1918 (Box LA11)
    - Account binder 8--Folder 1 of 4 (accounts payable record), 1923 Jan.-Nov. (Box LA11)
    - Account binder 8--Folder 2 of 4 (sale records), 1923 Feb.-Sept. (Box LA12)
    - Account binder 8--Folder 3 of 4 (sale records/check register), 1923 Aug.-Sept. (Box LA12)
    - Account binder 8--Folder 4 of 4 (check register), 1923 Aug.-Dec. (Box LA12)
    - Account binder 9--Folder 1 of 7 (accounts payable record/sales record/cash received), 1911 Aug.-Dec. (Box LA13)
    - Account binder 9--Folder 2 of 7 (cash received/accounts payable record/sales record), 1911 Aug.-1912 June (Box LA13)
    - Account binder 9--Folder 3 of 7 (sales record/check register, 1911 Oct. (Box LA14)
    - Account binder 9--Folder 4 of 7 (cash received/personal account record/sales record), 1913 Mar.-Nov. (Box LA14)